The honeymoon phase for vibe coding is
over and the new paradigm for AI coding
is context engineering. I truly believe
this is going to be the next big thing
for AI as a whole. And let me show you
why. So starting off earlier this year,
Andre Karpathy coined the term vibe
coding. It's all about relying 100% on
your AI coding assistant to build
applications for you with barely any
input and no validation. And this
concept completely blew up. We all fell
for this trap because of the dopamine
hit of instant code generation and also
because vibe coding is great for
weakened hacks and prototypes.
Basically, you rely on intuition and
repetition until your code seemingly
works, at least until you try to
productionize and scale it and then
suddenly it doesn't. And you can read
these statistics all over the internet.
One article that I appreciate in
particular is the state of AI code
quality from Codto. They did a massive
survey across the developer landscape.
You can see in the bottom purple
quadrant here, 76.4 of real developers
have low confidence shipping AI code
without human review. And they encounter
a lot of hallucinations. And it's not
like AI coding itself is bad. I mean, I
love it myself. It's vibe coding. AI
code without human review that is the
problem. Because here's the thing,
intuition does not scale. Structure
does. I heard that recently. I thought
it was so beautifully put. Because the
biggest problem that we have with AI
coding assistants right now is around
context. Often times they miss or lack
it entirely. So they don't have the
necessary context to get the job done.
We need better context. We need
structure. That is where context
engineering comes in. So let's kick
things off right now by diving into what
context engineering is. Then after we'll
get into the lab with claude code. I'll
show you how it works for real with a
practical example that you can use as a
template to instantly improve your AI
coding. This is not theoretical. For
some reason, YouTube has been obsessed
with the Gemini CLI recently. Meanwhile,
context engineering has been blowing up
everywhere else on the internet, and
context engineering is definitely a lot
more important. Like I always say,
capabilities over tools. The Gemini CLI
is a tool. Context engineering is a very
important capability that should really
dictate the way that you work with AI as
a whole. And context engineering was
even condoned by Andre who originally
coined Vibe coding. This is his response
to a tweet from Toby, the CEO of
Shopify, where he's comparing context
engineering to prompt engineering. We'll
talk about that in a second, but I
really love his definition here. It is
the art of providing all the context for
the task to be plausibly solvable by the
LLM. Here's a paradigm shift with this
context which is our instructions and
rules, documentation, so on that
deserves the respect to be treated as an
engineered resource requiring careful
architecture just like everything else
in software. When AI coding assistants
fail, it's most often because they just
don't have the information they need.
And no, I'm not just talking about
prompt engineering. Context engineering
is very much a step up. Like Toby is
saying, prompt engineering is all about
tweaking wording, phrasing things in a
specific way to get a single good answer
from the LLM. But context engineering,
supplying all relevant facts, rules,
documents, plans, tools. So the LLM has
a whole ecosystem of context. That is
the paradigm shift from basic prompting
and vibe coding. Prompting is just one
piece of the bigger picture that we have
here. And one last thing in X, I thought
this was really funny. The top comment
from Andre's reply to Toby is saying
context engineering is the new vibe
coding. And then Andre replied by saying
he's not trying to coin a new word. But
Andre, if you're watching this, I think
it is too late. I'm sorry. There is a
reason that people hang on to every word
that you say. Thank you for everything
that you do in the AI space. But anyway,
if you are a visual learner, I also
found this beautiful diagram in GitHub
on context engineering. So all the
different components that we have in
here together make up what context
engineering is. So we have prompt
engineering as a part of it like we
already talked about. We have structured
output. It's a way to make the output of
AI agents and coding assistants more
reliable. We have state history and
memory. So agents and coding assistants
be able to remember what they built in
the past. We can do things like provide
examples. And then also rag is a huge
component of context engineering. not
something that I'm going to be focusing
on a ton in this video, but that's
actually because I have a lot more
coming soon for you for rag and context
engineering, being able to supply
external documentation and knowledge to
our AI coding assistants. And I will say
there is a lot that is going on here. If
you want to really do context
engineering, well, you have to put a lot
of time up front creating this context
for your AI coding assistant. It's a lot
different than vibe coding where you
generally dive right into the actual
coding. But I always love to quote
Abraham Lincoln here. He said, "If you
give me six hours to chop down a tree,
I'm going to spend the first four
sharpening my axe." And that is exactly
what we are doing here. And it is well
worth your time to invest upfront into
creating this context because you're
going to get infinitely better results
versus diving straight into the
implementation. You're going to have
better code. You're going to actually
save a lot of time in the end and then
just not have to go through as much
pain. That is the whole point. That is
what I want to show you in action in a
little bit here. And the very last
article that I want to show you is the
rise of context engineering from lang
chain. This is definitely worth a read.
So I'll link to this in the description
of the video. And actually everything
that I shared with you here I'll link in
the description. I've definitely been
doing a deep dive into context
engineering. I hope that's very obvious
to you. And so their definition of
context engineering is pretty cool
because it aligns very very closely with
what we've seen already. But this is the
key paragraph that I want to focus on
here. LLM applications are evolving from
single prompts to more complex dynamic
agentic systems. And then here is the
real kicker. As such, context
engineering is becoming the most
important skill an AI engineer can
develop. That is a bold claim. Maybe
it's a bit of an exaggeration. I don't
really know if it's the most important
skill, but yeah, this just shows the
theme that's starting to emerge here
where context engineering certainly
feels like the thing to focus on right
now. And so with that, let's now dive
into cloud code. I'll show you how we
can implement this for real to get some
insane results with AI coding
assistance. So here is my template for
you in a GitHub repository that I'll
have linked in the description. My
introduction to context engineering. Now
you can get very very deep with context
engineering, diving into rag and memory,
things that I'll cover a lot more in the
near future here. What I want to do with
this is introduce you to the idea of
using AI coding assistance to create a
super comprehensive plan for a new
project and then implement that. And
we're going to be using cloud code. This
is going to work for really any AI
coding assistant, but I'm focusing on
cloud code here because it is the most
agentic and widely considered the most
powerful AI coding assistant right now.
And we're going to use cloud code to
plan, create the tasks, code, write
tests, and iterate on that all end to
end so that after just a few prompts, we
have a full project implemented for us.
That is the power that we have with
context engineering. And by the way, a
lot of what I'm about to dive into with
you here is inspired by someone in the
Dynamis community, Raasmus. He did a
workshop last month in our community and
it was an absolute killer. It was so
awesome. He covered his agentic coding
process focusing a lot on cloud code. He
did a lot of things related to context
engineering and he actually open sourced
a lot of the resources that he shared
with us in the workshop. So I'll link to
this in the description as well. So
credit where credit is due. Raasmus has
inspired a lot of my ideas. And also if
you want to dive a lot more into
building AI agents using AI coding
assistance, things like context
engineering, definitely check out
dynamis.ai. It is the place to be. We're
constantly pushing the limit of what's
possible with workshops like this. And
so with that, back into my template that
I have for you in the readme here, I
have a quick start. You can follow along
with this in just like 10 minutes and
level up your AI coding game that fast
with context engineering. But then also,
I have this repo cloned locally. I'm
just going to walk you through exactly
what we're doing here. And then we'll
see a demo in action. Now, before we
move on, I just want to mention really
quickly that there are definitely a lot
of security risks when using AI coding
assistance that are super important for
you to keep in mind. It doesn't matter
if you're using Cloud Code or Windsurf
or something else like GitHub Copilot.
These risks crop up that you might not
even be aware of. Things like prompt
injection, model poisoning, data
leakage, these aren't theoretical
threats anymore. That is why Sneak, a
company that is trusted for securing AI
generated code, is hosting a free live
webinar Tuesday, July 15th at 11:00 a.m.
Eastern time covering the OASP top 10
for LLMs. This is an event that you
don't want to miss. A clear breakdown of
these critical vulnerabilities. You get
to see live defenses against these
attacks like model poisoning and prompt
injection and learn best practices for
avoiding these security issues with AI
code. Vendanna Verma from Sneak is going
to be walking us through best practices
for handling AI generated code and
showing us real world examples that you
can apply immediately. Plus, if you're
an ISC2 member, you get one CPE credit
just for attending. It doesn't matter
where you're at with your technical
ability. If you are using AI coding
assistance, you have to understand these
risks. So, I have a link in the
description to register. Again, this is
Tuesday, July 15th at 11:00 a.m.
Eastern, and I'm definitely going to be
there myself. So I have the repo cloned
locally. Now let's dive into creating a
super comprehensive plan for a new
project and implementing it end to end
with cloud code. And like I said,
context engineering can be decently
involved up front. So there are quite a
few different files that I want to cover
here. Markdown files for all the
instructions, the different parts of our
context. And so the first file that I
want to cover is our claude.md.
These are the global rules for our AI
coding assistant. similar to, you know,
winds surf rules or cursor rules if
you've used those AI idees before. This
is the highest level information that we
want to give to our AI coding assistant.
Things like best practices that we want
it to follow, the way that we want it to
write tests for our project, um the way
that we want it to manage tasks, the
style and convention guides, like all of
this highle information we want to put
in claw.md.
And then going back to the readme here,
the next file that I want to cover is
our initial MD. This is where we
describe the feature that we wanted to
implement as it kicks off the project
for us. And so going into this, I very
much have it as a template for you. It's
just a few different sections for you to
fill out. So first, you want to describe
at a high level the feature that you
want implemented by cloud code or your
AI coding assistant. So something like I
want to build an AI agent that does ABC
built with XYZ. And it's worth being
pretty detailed in this section. And
then second, it's so so important
whenever you can provide examples to the
AI coding assistant. This just helps so
much. And so this could be from past
projects that you've worked on that have
some similar implementations for what
you want to build now. It could be code
examples or snippets that you found
online. You just want to put that in
this examples folder. And so I have this
in the repo specifically to call out
like this is your place to add examples
for your AI coding assistant. And then
also getting into the rag part of
context engineering, we have
documentation. So listing out any online
docs that you want the AI coding
assistant to reference or any MCP
servers for rag that you wanted to use
like my crawl for AAI rag for example.
I'm not going to be focusing on this too
much right now, but it still is a very
crucial part of context engineering. And
then last but not least, a place for any
other kinds of considerations that you
have for your AI coding assistant. And
this is a really good place to include
any gotchas, things that AI coding
assistants mess up on a lot in your
experience, just specifying how to avoid
that right here. And so what I'm going
to do for this build, because I am going
to show you a full example here, is I'm
actually going to delete initial.md and
I'm going to rename the example that I
have in the repo because we're going to
use this to build out an AI agent here.
And so going to initial.md, I'm building
an AI agent with pideantic AI. I have
some examples that I'll add into the
folder off camera. For the
documentation, I'm just going to have it
reference Pantic AI. And usually I'd
want to use an MCP server for rag, but
I'm just keeping it simple here. Um, and
then just for some other considerations
here, some things that I haven't messed
up on quite a bit is the use of
environment variables. I'm telling it to
make sure that it has a project
structure in a readme. So, just little
things like that. Just a couple of
examples that I wanted to give here. So,
that is my initial MD. And so now going
back to the readme, we have our global
rule set up. We have our initial prompt.
Now it is time to generate a full plan
for our implementation. And this is
where we get into two of my favorite
things for context engineering. Cloud
code/comands and PRPS, which is short
for product requirements prompts. And so
they're similar to product requirements
documents, PRDs. You've probably heard
of this before if you've been diving
into AI coding, but they are
specifically designed to instruct an AI
coding assistant. So, we're not creating
like an architecture document. We're
actually creating a prompt that we're
going to run with cloud code. So, we use
cloud code to build a prompt which is
part of the project plan and then we use
that to actually do the implementation
end to end. It's so so powerful and
we're using slash commands to take care
of this. So we don't have to prompt a
lot of things from scratch every time
we're using this process to begin a
project. And so in thecloud folder, if
you have a folder called commands, any
of the markdown files that you have here
can be executed as custom commands for
cloud code. It is a beautiful thing. And
so our first command here is generate
PRP. This is a prompt to create a very
comprehensive plan as another prompt for
cloud code. So there's a multi-step
process here. We're getting a little bit
more involved here now with context
engineering. And so I'm not going to go
through the details of this entire
document, but we're walking it through
what it looks like to take in a feature
requirements. We're going to actually
pass in initial MD and then do a bunch
of research on our behalf, some
architectural planning. We're having it
really think through the problem step by
step here to create a comprehensive plan
for implementation. This is the
engineered context that I'm really
getting at with context engineering. And
so the way this works and I'm going to
go into my terminal here and I'm going
to open up claude. When we have our
commands within the commands folder now,
I can do slashgenerate PRP and then the
argument that I want to pass in here.
This is just anything that I enter after
a space. This is what's going to be
given and it's going to replace the
arguments placeholder here. So if I say
initial.m
MD, I'm now telling this command that
the feature file is going to be
initial.md. So now cloud code is going
to look at initial.m MD, use that to
guide the feature that it is then going
to plan. So I'm going to go ahead and
run this right now. And this will take a
good amount of time because cloud code
really goes through this in a
comprehensive way, making sure that it
generates a complete PRP for us. And by
the way, it is also using a PRP template
that I have available in the PRPS
folder. So this is kind of its starting
point. This is the template that it
bases the whole document off of that it
produces after we are done with this
command. And so I'm going to pause and
come back once it's generated the PRP.
Then we'll take a look at what that
looks like and use it to build our
project. All right. So I'm coming back
just for a second here to show you the
process in action. The thing that I love
about using PRPs and just context
engineering in general is watching these
relatively large to-do lists that it
builds autonomously and knocks out one
at a time. And so what it's doing is
researching different APIs on my behalf
to really make sure that the PRP we
generate for implementation has all the
details necessary to not hallucinate the
usage of APIs. And that's one of the
biggest things that AI coding assistants
mess up on a lot. And so it's doing
research, analyzing the existing
codebase and then the examples that
we're giving it, reviewing
documentation, pantic AI, creating the
PRP based on that, writing it all, and
then it is done. There's so much that
it's taking care of here. Not just
creating one markdown file, but all of
the research and planning that it does
beforehand. And so yeah, now I will come
back once it is complete. And there we
go. Our PRP has now been implemented.
It's in research emailagent.mmd in the
PRPS folder. So it gives us a summary of
its research and analysis, some things
it did for the environment setup to get
things ready to implement the project,
and then it describes the content at a
high level. And so I definitely don't
want to dive in and explain everything
that it creates here. And this is like
brand new for me too. Um, but just going
through this, it describes core
principles, the primary goal for this
project, and success criteria. A lot of
specifics here that make a huge
difference. And a lot of this is based
off of the PRP base template that I uh
used from Raasmus. And then talks about
all the different documentation
referencing both websites and things
that I have in the examples folder that
I included off camera like I said I
would do. And man, this is just so
powerful because now that we list these
things and we instruct it in the PRP to
look at each of these files and
websites, we're going to have that all
in the context as it's coding
everything. And that's going to reduce
hallucinations a lot. Even just this
part alone is so powerful. And then
another thing that I really like is we
describe the current code base, what it
looks like right now, and then our
desired code bases. So we're laying out
every single file that we want to have
created ahead of time. And we're still
flexible enough where like it can change
the structure if it deems that worth
doing in the middle of implementing. But
yeah, this just shows the kind of
architecture planning that we're doing
ahead of time. It's so powerful. And so
with that, going back to the readme
here, there's really just one last step
that I want to show you. We've already
did a lot of context engineering. This
PRP, this is the pinnacle of context
engineering, at least what I want to
introduce you to right now. And so going
back to the readme, if I go down to the
bottom, now that we have the command run
for generate PRP, now we just want to
execute the PRP. It's very, very simple.
There's not much that we have to type
within cloud code itself because we are
doing all the planning in these markdown
files. We have our initial planning and
initial MD. We're generating a PRP with
this command and then executing it with
this one. And all the prompting just
lives in those files. And so now I can
literally do slashexecute PRP and then
if I open up my full terminal here, then
what I can do is reference PRPS slash
and then research email agent.m MD. So
just calling out where that exists in my
codebase. And then I'll send that in and
it's going to go ahead and create
another decently long task list. This is
going to be very very end to end. And so
I'm going to pause in a second and come
back once it is done implementing. But
I'll show a screenshot right here of the
task list that it creates. It's very
very comprehensive. That's the goal that
we have with this. It's so cool how
agentic our AI coding assistance can be
when we give it the right context and
how much we can reduce hallucinations as
well. And so I will come back once we
have the first version of our agent
created. And there we go. After more
than 30 minutes, Claude code has
completed and tested our agent end to
end. That is the power of agent coding
with cloud code and context engineering.
And it did take quite a few tokens to do
this to say the least. So I'll have a
screenshot right here of the token usage
in the middle of the development towards
the end. But I'm not bringing my own API
key. I'm taking advantage of the max
plan for Claude. And so I didn't have to
pay anything more for it to do all this
work for me. It is a beautiful thing.
And so yeah, this is the output here at
the end describing what it did for us.
There is one bit of iterating that I had
to do here. There's some weirdness for
how the tools were set up for the agent.
like it was creating these functions as
dependencies for the agent which isn't
really how you're supposed to do it with
padantic AI. So I did one round of
iterating but that was it and everything
is working really really well. And so I
do like I just did I highly recommend
not vive coding actually validating the
output but if you validate the output
have your context engineering set up you
are set. And so yeah we can go into the
terminal here. I can run pi test. So we
can see all of the tests that it created
and used to iterate on our agent.
Everything is passing. Just a couple of
warnings that we can ignore. And then
also we can run our CLI. So, I followed
the instructions that it created in the
readme for me to set things up and I
implemented my environment variables.
And so, now I can run Python CLI.py.
We're connected to our agent running
GBT4.1 Mini for our model. And you could
really use any model that you want.
Actually, one of the things that I had
in my examples was showing how to make
it so you can set up different providers
for your podantic AI agent like Gemini
or Olama or OpenAI. So, we can actually
do that as well. It's really cool. And
so, within here, I can just say hello.
We can test a basic message to our
agent. Looking really good. We got our
output here. Our terminal is looking
really beautiful. And I can say
something like search the web for the
latest
on clawed code. So we can have it use
the web search tool because that's our
research agent. I'm not going to test
this out a ton right here. I'm just
showing you right now that like
everything is working. We're using the
Brave API. We're using the OpenAI API.
We got some results here. It's going to
spit out a response for us in a second.
It's just doing a lot of web searching
for us, I guess. And there we go. All
right, we got our response from our
agent. So, this is working really,
really well. Like I said, I just had to
iterate once. So, I just kicked off this
build and I set up all the permissions
ahead of time. So, I just went and, you
know, took my dog on a walk, came back,
and the agent was it done. And that's
what I'm showing you guys right here.
So, really, really cool. That is the
power of context engineering. And this
is just getting your feet wet. I very
much encourage you to use this template
that I have for you. dive into creating
these comprehensive plans and using them
with an AI coding assistant like cloud
code and then just take it from there.
There's so much more you can do with
context engineering with memory and
state and rag a lot of things that I
want to cover soon on my channel as
well. So you can really go down the
rabbit hole of context engineering and
like we talked about at the start of
this video it is really the thing to
focus on right now and so dive deep have
fun with it. I hope this helps as a
starting point for you as well. And so
if you appreciated this video and you're
looking forward to more things AI
coding, AI agents, and context
engineering, definitely give me a like
and a subscribe. And with that, I will
see you in the next